Zeughofstr. 1 10997 Berlin Germany

Email: jonas.markgraf@gmail.com
Website: jmarkgraf.netlify.app

Current Position

2020 - ongoing: Senior Economist, Zalando SE, Berlin.

Expert for causal identification, statistics, and experimentation in the Algorithmic Data Products team at Zalando's Offprice Data Platforms & AI department.

Responsibilities include: measuring the impact of changes to the pricing algorithm; improving demand elasticity model; enabling to steer investment decisions to create deep customer relationships; leading a team of three on interim basis (6 months).

Education

Dr. rer. pol. Political Science, Hertie School of Governance, 2015 - 2018.

Thesis: Politicians as Bankers: On the Mechanisms and Consequences of Politically Influenced Banking.

Grade: summa cum laude.

Committee: Mark Hallerberg (Hertie School of Governance); Guillermo Rosas (Washington University in St. Louis); Joachim Wehner (London School of Economics).

o1/- o6/2017: Pre-Doctoral Research Fellow, Political Science Department, Washington University in St. Louis (sponsor: Guillermo Rosas).

11/2016: Short-Term Visiting Scholar, Juan March Institute, Carlos III University, Madrid.

M.Sc. International Political Economy, London School of Economics, 2013 - 2014.

B.A. Political Science & Economics, Free University Berlin, 2009 - 2013.

2011-2012: Erasmus Exchange, University of Kent, UK.

Previous Positions

2019 - 2020: Policy Advisor, Federal Ministry of Finance, Berlin.

Economic advisor in the Directorate-General "Financial Market Policy" (Division: "International Anti-Money Laundering")

2018 - 2019: Postdoctoral Research Fellow, University of Oxford, Oxford.

ERC-funded research project WEALTHPOL on wealth inequality with Prof. Ben Ansell & Research fellow at Nuffield College

Responsibilities included: designing and implementing lab and survey experiments; quantitative data/text analysis; writing scientific papers and policy briefs; communicating results to diverse audiences; supervising PhD students.

2015 - 2018: Research Associate, Hertie School of Governance, Berlin.

Research Project "Public Finance Through Public Banks" with Prof. Mark Hallerberg.

Responsibilities included: conceptualization of research project; presentation of findings; data collection.

2014 - 2015: Consultant Market Analyst, International Trade Centre (UN / WTO), Geneva.

ITC-European Commission Business Survey on Non-Tariff Measures in the EU "Navigating Non-Tariff Measures"

Responsibilities included: coordination of survey launch; implementation of survey; organization and conducting of multi-day training workshops; survey design.

Publications

Refereed Journal Articles

- 3. "Backscratching in Banks: Politically Motivated Appointments of Bank Managers.", Political Science Research and Methods, Early View
- 2. "On Board With Banks: Do Banking Connections Help Politicians Win Elections?" (with Guillermo Rosas), *The Journal of Politics*, 2019, (81) 4, 1357–1370.
- 1. "The Corporate Governance of Public Banks Before and After the Global Financial Crisis: Examples from Germany, Italy, and Spain." (with Mark Hallerberg), *Global Policy*, 2018, (9) S1, 43–53 (Special Issue)

Working Papers

"Borrowing Welfare: Credit Access and Support for Redistribution." (with Guillermo Rosas), invited to Revise & Resubmit at *The Journal of Politics*

"Electoral Cycles in Bank Lending Explained: The Role of Political Representation in Governing Bodies." (with Till Stowasser)

"Voting Against Democracy: Feudalism and the Weimar Republic." (with Anselm Hager)

Ongoing Projects

"How do wealth and income affect individuals' attitudes towards redistribution and taxation?" (with Ben Ansell, Laure Bokobza, Asli Cansunar, Mads Elkjaer, & Jacob Nyrup)

"How Credit Markets Shape Beliefs About a Just Redistributive System" (with Andreas Wiedemann)

Policy Contributions

The Distribution of Income and Wealth in Advanced Economies., WEALTHblog, University of Oxford, 2019.

Germany's savings banks: uniquely intertwined with local politics. (with Nicolas Veron), Bruegel, 2018.

Conference Participation and Presentations

2020: APSA; PolMeth.

2019: EPSA; APSA; Dreilaendertagung.

2018: EPSA; MPSA; APSA; CES; SVPW; Dezernat Zukunft (invited talk); German Savings Bank Association (invited talk).

2017: EPSA; MPSA; SLAMM; Ronald Coase Workshop Bogota.

2016: Universidad Autonoma Barcelona (invited talk); Global Finance Workshop; CEU Graduate Network Conference.

Fellowships & Grants

2019: John Fell Research Grant (Co-PI: Andreas Wiedemann) (£7,000).

2019: John Fell Research Grant & Nuffield College Politics Group (Co-PI: Andreas Wiedemann & Asli Cansunar) (£9,600).

2018: Weidenbaum Center Research Grant (PI: Guillermo Rosas) (\$3,000).

2018: Postdoctoral Swiss Government Excellence Scholarship, 2018-19 (CHF42,000) (declined).

2017: Ronald Coase Fellowship funding workshop participation (\$2,000).

2017: NASP Young Investigator Program funding participation at EITM & EPSA, ACRI (€ 3,000).

2014 - 2015: Carlo Schmid Scholarship for Fellowships in International Organizations, DAAD & Studienstiftung des Deutschen Volkes (~€ 10,000).

Additional Training

2019: "Intermediate Causal Inference (Sensitivity & Placebo Testing)", Andy Eggers, University of Oxford.

2016 & 2019: "Quantitative Text Analysis", Heike Klüver, Humboldt University/Tom O'Grady, UCL.

2018: "Web Data Collection and Social Media Mining", Simon Munzert, Hertie School of Governance.

2017: "Empirical Implications of Theoretical Models (EITM) Europe Summer School", Turin.

2017: "Applied Statistical Programming", Jacob Montgomery, Washington University in St. Louis.

2017: "Longitudinal and Event History Models", Jeff Gill, Washington University in St. Louis.

2016: "Causal Inference in the Social Science", Elias Dinas, ECPR Summer School, Budapest.

Skills

Software: R, Stata, IATEX, GitHub, SQL, Microsoft Excel (all advanced), Qualtrics, Python (intermediate), JavaScript (basic)

Languages: German (mother tongue), English (fluent), Russian (moderate), French (moderate)

References

Ben Ansell

Professor of Comparative Democratic Institutions, University of Oxford.

Mark Hallerberg

Professor of Public Management and Political Economy, Hertie School of Governance.

Guillermo Rosas

Professor of Political Science, Washington University in St. Louis.